I was going to go.
And a wonderful-
There's a little whoopsie. I couldn't get out. Yeah, hold on.
Luckily, I had a free time.
Right.
Okay. So we're now onto item three, which is the Ngā Hapū o Te
Ihua finally claim settlement bill,
and we have a number of submitters in front of us.
Clearly, this is submissions to be heard here in
Wellington, and we'll have another opportunity in Tāmannui on
Monday. That's correct, Jonathan, on Monday.
But as per usual, as per convention, we ask for
the
settlement trust to have some opening comments, and I can
see them online. So,
tena koroa. I can see two of you there. Keen, and others. Yep.
Tena koroa.
So yeah, just to begin with, we'll provide you with approximately 10
minutes
to open up this proceeding. So away you go.
You're on mute. Now you're right. Sweet. Thank you.
Tihei mauri ora.
Karanga, karanga ki a Ranginui e tū i konei.
Karanga, karanga ki a Papā e takoto ake nei.
Kia raru ngā tapuwae o te tangata, hei putanga ariki, hei putanga
tauira. Kia ora pai ai te ara kupu matua,
ngā rongo, ngā tāne, ngā rehua.
Ka p**a ki ngā utapu o Tāwhirimātea ki te waiao, ki te ao
mārama. Ei rongo e waka iri ia. Turuturu au i
te waka mau ake atu ngā-
Kei ngā.
Kia oi e.
Tāiki e.
Tauriori kau ana te taie o te tangata kei wera rā tāhunga
mai o te kora.
Kei te rangi ikitia, kei te rangi āpaingia.
Kei te wa a ātaei. Kei a Ranginui e tū nei.
Kei a Papā e takoto nei. Uea,
uea.
Tākirikiri mai ana te pūa o te ata tū kōrongo
kōrua pēia. Ka wakareu te
titiro
ki te kāui kauika kua paia ki te ākau o te ikanu.
Ka ruru ana te tai ki ngā rekareka o te maunga.
Kīhai e nekeneke.
I tēnā o ngā piki amokura ka whatia mai rā.
Koia, ko Tāmiti.
Meira waka runga ki te rohe o Mātātuawaka.
Ki te matarai ki koe.
Koia ko Tāhirini.
Hoki mai rā ki runga o te tai uru, ki te
kōtiiti o Tararua. Koia te āhuarangi ko
Whatarangi.
Huri atu ki a rātou, koutou,
ngā mateuuo o te wā.
E takoto ana ki runga āuna i mahā o te ikanu, o te ikaro.
Witia atu te moana o Raukawa ki te waka āorangi.
Tua atu ki Wharekao.
He tai, he tai wau ano, reua. Taimi ngā
tangata, taimi ngā roa.
Nō reira oti atu koutou ki te pō. Nau mai te ao.
Nei rā te mihi atu ki a koutou
e te rangamataraura
o te komiti tā.
Te peiro o te komiti ana.
Kua taupuhitia nei
hei kaituruki, hei kaiwete wete mō te ia kōrero o te ranginui.
Ka hoki aku whakaaro
ki te kōrero ki tā Rangiti tau pāra.
Ina te urunga o ngai tātou kei raro i ngā kauae
mātauranga o tau iwi.
Kua onotia te peka Māori ki te rākau rawa
o. Kua p**a he ua tauau.
Hei kawa tonāreka.
Nō reira e tika ana i roto i tēnei rā
mā koutou te rārangi matua ki te onepu hei
wāwae.
Kia mārama i tātau.
Kei tērā taha o te rārangi, ana
ko te tikanga o te matua iwi.
Kei tērā tāhā o te rārangi.
Koia
te kawa
o te ua tauau.
Nō reira tēnei te reo
o ngā hapū o te iwi o Whanganui.
Ngā kawa o uta, ngā tore o taia.
Mai pīpiri ki tae atu ki te pūa o Whanganui, e mihi atu ki a
koutou. E mihi ana. E mihi ana. E mihi
ana.
Tēnā,
tuia tuia, uia uiui.
Tuia ngā moko o te taurawiri ariki.
Uiā ngā moko o te taurawiri poropiti.
Ka rongo te pō, ka rongo te ao. Nō
reira i te uiuinga i te tuituinga. Koutou tātou e pai
nei. Tēnā koutou,
tēnā koutou, ka haere. Tēnā anō tātou katoa.
Kia ora.
Kia
ora.
Nō reira i tū anei tēnei wā o
tērā tuatahi kei te mea kia, kia,
kia tātou. Me kī,
kia tātou
Tōkana, whakatū wera tēnei kaupapa i runga ngā
kupu mō tēnei wā. Hei aha hei āwhina, hei tautoko ki te
kaupapa. Ngā kaupapa e mōhio tātou i tēnei ahiahi, me kī
mō tēnei wiki e heke mai nei. Nō reira haere tonu ngā mihi
ki a koutou, David.
Rua Nui, me kī.
Kei te kō, kei te haritona ahau e whakatakoto
ngā whakaaro e pā ana ki tēnei kaupapa e mōhio tātou i tēnei wā, me kī ki a
koutou katoa.
Willie koutou,
kei te kō, kei te haritona ahau.
Otirā,
e tuana mō tēnei wā koto,
iti, me kī.
Ko tēnei te wā o te timatanga o te tau hou, me kī.
Ngā mihi ki a koutou. Ko te tau hou
o Puaka, Matariki rānei. Nō reira, tēnā
koutou katoa.
Just picking up,
David, our intentions is not to
give our submissions
today. We're going to wait till
our pūtiki, where we can see everybody, ā-tinana,
ā-wairua, Willie,
in regard to our submissions there.
And David, we can only see Dr. Vanessa,
Willie, and yourself. We're not quite sure who else is
part of your committee.
Steve,
Georgie, lovely to see youse. And we've got
the majority of our trustees here as well in attendance,
just in the context of listening only.
It's not our intentions to respond or articulate any
issues that may come about today. If there are questions
that the select committee require,
we're happy to address those when we're at pūtiki with
yourselves, only if you require our responses.
But that's not where our headspace is.
So koinā ngā whakarite, me kī,
i tēnei wā. Nō reira tēnā koutou katoa.
Tēnā koroua, e te rangatira o Whanganui iwi.
So yeah, okay then. So thank you for that to you both, for the
nice greeting as well as giving us an understanding of where that
is. So yeah, Keen, we will give you time if you
choose to, and if we've got questions at the end of today's
hearing process, which it seems that's a bit of a convention that
we have as a committee to allow the settlement trust to be able to
respond to anything that may have actually been brought forward in the
proceedings itself. But with that, we will move straight on to
the next submission, and that's from Te Patu
tokotoko.
And are they-- Are they online? Yeah. Tēnā koe, Hayden. Kia ora.
Hayden, so we've got 10 minutes allocated to you today.
We've had an opportunity to read your submission, but this is your opportunity
to press upon the important parts of what you're submitting yourself.
So kia ora mai.
Mō tena tatou, ā, e oti noa, ā, Turama, te
tuakana. Ko wā, wā i pai ai tō tātou hui.
Mihi nui ki a koe, me ngā whakaaro ki rātou
mā, ngā ika nui o te wā, me
kī, koinei ngā i rei i roto i te wa iti nei.
E wai atu tonu i te ara ko Papatauri o tō
tātou rangatira, tō tātou ariki
Uncle Tumu, rātou mā kua hinga
i roto i tēnei tau, tēnei tonu mātou e tangi.
He oti noa, ā, koutou te poari, mihi nui ki a koutou.
Kare tae te kite te katoa o tō rōpū, engari
mihi kau atu ki a koutou-
A koe hoki
... kātika.
Hare te mea ka pānui i taku reta, engari
kia whakarāpopoto noa i aku kupu.
So yeah, thank you, everybody. I
won't read you through the submission before you,
but just touch on some key points. I think fundamentally,
the first point I really want to make is that Patu Tokotoko are
in support
of the settlement.
We are in support of the approach our leadership
has taken
in the early stages of ratification.
Prior to that in seeking mandate,
and of course, in the establishment of the PSGE.
We're in support of the trust deed,
and
quite excited by the fact
that we're now advancing into this period of our history.
Really excited about the redress,
as well as the redress coming from adjacent parties like the Wanganui District
Council.
I wanted to take time to acknowledge the leadership
of our whole trust and board, specifically Ken Mear,
as well as key drivers
like Amy Simon,
Tracy Waitokia,
as well as all of our kaumatua kuia
who have led us on this pathway for a long time, and some no
longer with us, and so just wanted to acknowledge
their efforts alongside the Runanga o Tamu Pok and Tupou.
The substantive matter before us, however, for Patu
Tokotoko is
what I guess I'd call
unintended consequences.
And
we are,
I guess, an anomaly in this treaty settlement space,
because, and you'll see on my
submission, even the Crown acknowledges us as a pan-tribal
collective of hapu,
and it is quite a different makeup than I think the
PSGs or that settlement process had really
considered. And so it led to, without our
doing, I might add,
us being
or becoming shared hapū of essentially four
or five entities.
That is because Whanganui, Matua Iwi is
a whole collective, but our approach to settlement was through large natural
groupings, Patutokotoko connecting to our whole
river from the maunga to the sea. And
yeah, so
what we've seen is the process wasn't necessarily--
You're all au fait with treaty settlement processes, and they
can at times be quite adversarial.
They can be competitive, and they can compete for things like
statutory overlay,
resource,
land, and other things that come alongside settlement.
And so that process through those
land settlement entities
at time became political, and our hapū never
really played a strong part in that process,
but have eventually came out as a shared hapū of Ngāti Rangi, a
shared hapū of Te Koro Wai or Wainuiārua,
a shared hapū of
Whanganui Land Settlement, now Takapau Ariki.
We are named in the Ngā Tangata Tiaki settlement as
Patutokotoko and Ngāti Peke Tūroa.
And our previous name as a hapū before it was
called Patutokotoko was called Ngāti Hekeāwai, which is also a shared hapū
of Ngāti Hauā. Prior to that, it was Ngāti Rua Kōpiri, and
prior to that it was Ngāti Rua Tipua, prior to that it
was Te Kāhui a Maui. So for a long time we've been a part of
this
iwi. And
where it comes interesting is in the
articulation of historical accounts.
Some of the history is told to suit the lens of that particular
entity going through its particular negotiation with the settlement
or with the Tarawhiti and those groups.
We
also experienced some direct
conflict with the Crown. In fact, at times the Crown
directly targeted our tūpuna from the
Tūroa family. And if you go back and look through the
apologies or the statements read out
at Kaiwhaiki just recently,
I think Kaurangi Simon articulates that
history quite clearly.
But in the apology within this particular settlement, it
doesn't acknowledge
that the Crown straight after the very first or
first two conflicts at Pukenamu
at Pātupāho,
it didn't
acknowledge that they went over to our koroua's whare at Kukutā
and burnt it down.
Donald McLean, who later gave a tokotoko on behalf of Queen Victoria,
which our family still hold,
he describes it as the most elaborately carved house
on the whole of the West Coast.
And that house was burnt down by Captain White,
I understand,
of the government army, and then they
torched Te Pihi Tūroa the First's
burial or urupā or it was a
waka that was placed at Kukutā and that was torched by the
government soldiers. Later on, the government then
led into Ōhautahi
and done a whole lot of campaigns after Motu where
they kind of used the excuse of us,
even though we didn't participate in the Motu battle, they used the
excuse of us harboring the refugees as essentially creating
Hauhauism. And because our family were directly associated with
the Kiingitanga that led to the Pipiriki siege and the
Ōhautahi battle where further Tūroa houses were burnt down and
pā occupied. This whole history of course
doesn't necessarily
play out in any one of these historical accounts.
And it is a really important history and our fear is
that it will lead to cultural erasure,
especially for agencies and groups who now are
referring to deeds of settlements for the historic accounts and the
like to understand how to engage
through their processes. And we've just been through a very
poor process led by Minister Pōtaka around the
Tūroa
ski field and the Whakapapa ski field, and we're currently going
through the High Court process on that matter.
But that ultimately has played into our fear of this cultural
erasure, misinterpretation of history and then therefore
overlooking rights and interests in modern-day
decision-making. So those are kind of the,
I guess the gist of some of the things we're pointing to in this submission.
I definitely don't want that to
cloud over the fact that we are deeply supportive of
this settlement. We have remained supportive of all settlements led
by the different LNGs and
yeah, do appreciate the leadership and energy that's gone into this.
So kōia te nuinga o āku kōrero. Ehara i te mea kia
aukumia tēnei āhuatanga.
You know-
... Nga. Nga reira tena koutou.
Kia ora. Okay, I'll open up for any questions from any of the
members of the committee. Steve, Steve Abel.
Yeah. Thank you very much, Hayden.
I think you articulate really excellently in your submission the
challenge of
which piece of history is focused on, and
how the network of those histories
may be lost
if the accounts aren't accurate. I wonder, what is the remedy that
you see in this instance?
Even in and of itself, the fact you've made
the submission puts it on the formal record.
I wonder if you can articulate what other remedies you think there could
be.
Yeah, thanks Steve. Yeah, we were deliberate in putting this on the record-
Mm
... because we know this may play out in generations to come, and we just
want something for our mokopuna to tether themselves to and see
that we've been responsible tupuna.
One thing that
actually Labor done under Minister
Kiritapu Allan at the time was set us forward
on a process of reconciliation. Not a settlement so
much, but investigating if we could have a process of reconciliation that
can look at this and say, "Hey, here's an anomaly here.
Can we embark on this journey?" And we made some really positive
steps towards that, Steve,
right up until this government came into power
and Minister Pōtaka and Minister Goldsmith almost just
wiped that whole process off, and we haven't been able to pick that up again.
And so, that's probably where
we'd love to see the leadership of people like Willie Jackson,
when this government does change, come in and support a process of
reconciliation.
Yeah, because we do think it is important.
We're not necessarily saying that it needs to mirror a
settlement or look like a financial return, but it does actually need to
go through a reconciliation, and the fact that our hapū still have
no
one single marae is a pain to our hapū,
and it's a journey that we're going on ourselves.
So, I think part of the way forward is a
process that we've got to enact through our rangatiratanga and grow
and we are doing that. But I think a reconciliation
or a way to actually say, "Look, here is a full, complete story on this
matter,"
that could help as well.
Kia ora, that's a very clear response. Thank you.
Thanks, Hayden. Any last questions?
It appears not. Hayden, hey, thank you very much.
By the way,
the submission provided by your--
has been very good. It was a very good read.
So, thank you for that submission.
You might want to make one more statement about the government.
Won't quite go there today.
But thank you, Hayden, for your time today. Kia ora.
No, thank you, everyone, for your time.
Kia ora. Right. We now move to Tania
Bailey.
Tena koe, Tania.
Kia ora.
Tena koe.
Tena koe. Thank you, Tania, and thank you also for resubmitting.
Yeah.
One of the roles we have as a committee is to make sure that the submissions are
within our standing orders.
Yeah.
And there were a number of submissions that we politely asked if they could
resubmit, and-
Oh, yeah
... we appreciate you doing the same as well.
We've received that resubmission.
We've received the two supporting documents as well.
Probably just to begin, we have a role here of trying to
strengthen the settlement bill as much as we
can.
I recognize the journey that you've been through and what you've identified-
Mm-hmm
... in your submission. It probably wouldn't come as a surprise to you, but a lot
of that we don't have a power of or
responsibility for.
Mm-hmm.
But we have read it, we've received it-
Mm-hmm
... and that, and would be appreciative if you could help us with this
bill that we have before us.
Okay.
We've got five minutes available for you.
Five minutes, okay.
Okay?
I did request 10 minutes for that-
You did request. We have a convention here as a committee that with groups
and individuals, we definitely received your submission as an
individual. I actually read through it again to see-
Yeah
... where it actually points to a-
I'm the chair of the koha shed.
Yeah. There's lots of members that would do.
We're just trying to keep the convention, otherwise we'll set a precedent that
could be rather dangerous for us in the future. So kia ora mai. Thank you.
Okay.
Cheers.
Tena koutou katoa, Mr. Chair, committee members.
He mokopuna tēnei nō Te Awanuiārua, nō Te
Kāui maunga, nō Ngāti Mutunga hoki, nō
Ngāpuhi, nō Te Rāhere hoki.
Mr. Chair, committee members. Ko Tania Aroha Bailey tōku
ingoa.
I'm here to carry the voices of many and in total opposition to this
bill.
I'm presenting first in Wellington today because I'm trespassed from my own marae,
Putiki Wharanui, for raising the very concerns that
are contained in this submission.
I'm a mokopuna of Te Rangi Paehā Tahi Metekingi who was the first
western Māori MP. I'm a direct uri of the
Putiki Tuakana lines,
Ngā Wāno Takarangi, Te Aonoa, Bailey,
Pātapu and Turoa. Putiki Wharanui is a
Takarangi marae that sits on Takarangi Street.
The whenua is registered to Takarangi Metekingi Whānau
and our Takarangi tūpuna fill the urupā.
Our Takarangi tūpuna are the closest to their marae.
I'm asking you to please do not rely on insider endorsements.
At least half of the supporting submissions have come in from the governance
group and their family, all motivated by self-interest, and
they will be the direct beneficiaries
I ask you to review the provided handout.
I ask you to take it to Pūtiki,
because this is about what they don't say,
and this will direct you to ask more objective questions.
I'm just going to go over five things.
So the mandate math is a fiction.
Proponents will claim 81% support, but if you look at the attachment
R, which is the funnel of exclusion, you will see that out
of 50,000 uri, this is just 1.6%.
On the adult register, if you want to look to the register, which
was over 8,000, then it's 10%.
But we want to know how
the register was cut down to 4,000 people.
So there was no
criteria and no appeal. So how did that happen?
Two, this is corporate dereliction, not iwi
politics. A hidden $1.4 million
council loan under secret personal
guarantees from the
lead negotiator and the project manager.
This is a severe breach of fiduciary duty, not internal
politics. Attachment K will show you the loan was concealed from whānau.
Attachment M confirms that public social services grants
are being diverted to pay the interest for a
personal loan.
Three, the
trustees are legally compromised.
Māori Land Court recently found the Pūtiki trustees were illegally
elected. A core negotiator is also under active police
investigation for theft of taonga.
Parliament cannot responsibly transfer millions to an
entity that is compromised by active judicial
and criminal inquiries.
Four, the bill triggers the doctrine of frustration.
The bill locks us into co-governance with the Whanganui District Council,
but under the May 26th directives of this government, the council
faces structural abolition by 2028.
Hapū are expected to partner with an entity that is scheduled to
disappear.
So basically you're agreeing to something that is legally
impossible
to achieve.
Five, they're rushing to beat the election clock.
Proponents are telling kaumatua the second reading is in August
to force a rush before the November
election, but yet this committee says its final report is the 12th of
November.
In conclusion, a bad settlement harms whānau more
than no settlement.
Many people have been excluded from this process.
As you will see, the numbers represent that.
None of the Koha Shed whānau, 500 whānau go through there a week, none
of them knew. We asked for support. We were rejected.
I'd like to talk more
about why you think that some of these things you can't address, but
proponents have leveraged Crown authority to turn
iwi collective assets into unaccountable
corporate fiefdoms.
Halt this bill and appoint an independent statutory manager.
And the Crown is on notice. Kia ora,
Tania.
Kia ora. Yeah, Puli.
Kia ora. Tēnā koe, Tania.
Kia ora.
Tell me about what sort of support do you think you've got at ground
level?
Oh, so are you talking about what mandate that I have, are you?
No, I'm just asking, have you got a lot of support?
Yes, I have. We've got a Facebook page called Pūtiki Legal that's got over 50
whānau on it.
I represent multiple whānau at the Koha Shed, and plus a lot of
Pūtiki whānau who have been excluded from this process and from their
marae.
So the process is,
and I was reading your submission,
your complaint is not dissimilar to many-
Mm-hmm
... who go through the process, right?
Yeah.
And so I acknowledge what you're saying in terms of those
numbers.
I mean, the
executive can only call for people to come and vote, right?
A lot of our people just don't turn up.
Don't you think that sometimes the iwi or the tribe, Tania, they've just got to get
on with it, do you think? Do you think they've just got to get on with it, rather
than wait?
No, I don't, Billy.
I understand your frustration.
No.
I'm not rubbishing where you're at, but it's the same
kōrero all the time through
this kaupapa. People don't come,
and so the iwi just have to get on with it, don't you think?
No, I don't. So are you telling me that everyone that comes through
here has
governance capture in their entities that ignore all of their
fiduciary duties and take out
$1.4 million loans with the council without telling anybody?
Is that normal?
No, I'm-
No
... talking about people who register in terms of the settlement, in terms of the
vote. Now-
What was your question about people registering?
I'm just saying that the process in terms of Treaty settlement, the
frustration you're showing is something that is quite
normal during Treaty settlement processes, right?
So people reg-- because you're saying, "Well, 850 have just registered,"
right? That's what you're saying.
And I'm saying to you that you can't force them to the table,
really.
I'm bringing you the math
Yeah
To show you, and it's not about mandate or who's registered
or what.
Mm.
This is the official information that shows we had
50,000 uri.
Mm. Mm.
And then that you can see quite clearly there's been a process of
exclusion to get a very nice number of 4,000, which means all they have
to do is get 1,000, which is 25% return.
So you're saying that-
I'm putting it to you that-
Yeah
... it didn't matter how many people responded because the
register has been altered to suit.
And it's all there. It's there in the information.
Okay. Any other questions from members?
What you're saying is a deliberate strategy of exclusion.
Mm-hmm.
Is that what you're saying?
Well, that would go along with the trustees who have failed to have
elections for 10 years, failed to release
financials,
hidden the $1.4 million loan that is personally secured by
three trustees.
Yeah. I don't know if that's normal practice.
I don't think it is.
Well, I'm not sure if they'd accept what you're saying. But anyway.
I'm sure they wouldn't. But I'd like to see the evidence, because we do have the
evidence, Willie, and it's right in front of you. It's in the documents.
Okay. So, hey, we've come to time, but I just want to let you know
you've got a number of points that you've made within your submission.
Part of the process of all submissions is that we get a
response.
Yeah.
We look at all of that, and we go through it along the line as-
Mm-hmm
... so. So once again, thank you very much for the time you've taken to
put the submission before us, and it will be looked at, and there'll be
questions being asked of it.
Okay.
Ngā mihi nui.
Kia ora.
Thank you.
Thank you. Ngā mihi nui.
You may put one on the next slide.
So we'll just return now to the Whanganui Land Settlement Negotiation Trust.
And as Ken said, they... Ken, you just need to
answer any questions at this time?
Is there any statements you wish to make at this point?
Just reiterate, David, what I said right at the beginning.
If there are any questions from the Select Committee required, we'd
prefer to
contemplate those over the next few days until we get to-
Yeah
... Putiki, and we respond to them in person if required.
Yeah.
And the only statement we have is to acknowledge
the submitters
today and appreciate that they've had that opportunity to
submit and, albeit we might have a different perspective, but we
seriously appreciate the fact that they've taken
the time and effort to
submit through this process.
Yeah. Good stuff. Okay. So committee members, any questions of
them at this time to take away? Maybe to wait to Putiki. Wait to Putiki.
Willie?
Well, you can answer some of the allegations if you like.
Yeah. I'm sure they'll want to respond to that. Sure. Yeah.
But there's no addition to that. Anything else?
No, I think they want to wait till we to the marae.
All right. All right. Yeah. So with that, Ken, and
we are going to be with you on Monday, and I imagine
the logistics have been worked out. I'm looking at my help here, Ken.
So that's all in order. So we're looking forward to catching up with you at
Putiki.
And can I just ask Turama to waka
kapi tenei kaupapa-
Ka pai.
Iki.
Iki iki ki te
ariari. Ki ngā
papai. Rangārangā
i a te tapu.
Taku waka nei e rere
uro.
Rere ā-manu rere tāke
tāke. Itua ki ē ua i
manaia. Pae ke ā
reira. Tāma ki tō ngā
whenua.
Tāma te tāma te
ema ema. Ka p**a kei tua
waowao kei ā.
Kei te moko
pūrangi. Kei te
waiao. Kei te
ao mārama. E
rongo waka e rere āki.
Turuturu āwiki waka mau ki ā tīnā.
Tīnā. Ā aumia ui e Tāiki.
Kia ora. Thank you. Kia ora.
See you on Monday.
Okay.
We will be now moving into commit- I notice we've got some students here.
Whereabouts are you guys from?
Chris High School in Hamilton.
Oh, very good. Welcome.
They're
part of... They're connected to me for
a couple of days, and they've come to see a selection.
Good stuff. Awesome. Well, welcome. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
But yeah, so
Jonathan, we'll move now into committee, and we'll go into the deliberations.
So I'm afraid we're going to have to-